<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Safety on Mind Traps: The Ultimate Guide to 150 Cognitive Biases</title>
    <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/tags/safety/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Safety on Mind Traps: The Ultimate Guide to 150 Cognitive Biases</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/tags/safety/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Risk Compensation</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/risk-compensation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/risk-compensation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Okay, here&amp;rsquo;s a blog post designed to fit your specifications, aimed at a professional, student, and lifelong learner audience, focused on the cognitive bias &amp;ldquo;Risk Compensation.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title: Risk Compensation: Why Feeling Safer Can Make You More Reckless&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(Meta Description: Risk Compensation is a cognitive bias that makes us take more risks when we feel safer. Learn how it works, why we fall for it, and how to overcome it in this insightful guide.)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zero-Risk Bias</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/zero-risk-bias/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/zero-risk-bias/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We all crave safety. The promise of eliminating danger entirely is inherently appealing. But what if our pursuit of absolute security actually makes us &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; safe in the long run? Enter &lt;strong&gt;Zero-Risk Bias&lt;/strong&gt;, a cognitive quirk that can lead us down inefficient, even harmful, paths.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;1-what-is-zero-risk-bias&#34;&gt;&#xA;  1. What is Zero-Risk Bias?&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#1-what-is-zero-risk-bias&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zero-Risk Bias&lt;/strong&gt; describes our tendency to prefer reducing a small risk to zero, even if a greater reduction in a larger risk is available. It&amp;rsquo;s the psychological equivalent of chasing pennies while dollars fly away.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
