<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Social-Comparison on Mind Traps: The Ultimate Guide to 150 Cognitive Biases</title>
    <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/tags/social-comparison/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Social-Comparison on Mind Traps: The Ultimate Guide to 150 Cognitive Biases</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/tags/social-comparison/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Illusory Superiority</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/illusory-superiority/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/illusory-superiority/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ever felt like you&amp;rsquo;re a better driver than most people on the road? Or that you’re more ethical, smarter, or more insightful than the average person in your workplace? Chances are you’ve experienced &lt;strong&gt;Illusory Superiority&lt;/strong&gt;, a sneaky cognitive bias that affects us all. Understanding this bias is crucial for better decision-making, improved relationships, and ultimately, a more accurate view of ourselves and the world. Let&amp;rsquo;s dive in.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;1-what-is-illusory-superiority&#34;&gt;&#xA;  1. What is Illusory Superiority?&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#1-what-is-illusory-superiority&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Illusory Superiority&lt;/strong&gt;, also known as the &amp;ldquo;above-average effect,&amp;rdquo; is the tendency to overestimate one&amp;rsquo;s desirable qualities and abilities while simultaneously underestimating one&amp;rsquo;s undesirable qualities, relative to other people. In simpler terms, we tend to think we’re better than average in various domains.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Worse-Than-Average Effect</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/worse-than-average-effect/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/worse-than-average-effect/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We all have moments of self-doubt. But what if that doubt consistently tells you you&amp;rsquo;re worse than average, especially when tackling difficult tasks? You might be experiencing the &lt;strong&gt;Worse-Than-Average Effect&lt;/strong&gt;, a cognitive bias that subtly undermines our confidence and distorts our perception of our own abilities. Let’s dive into what it is, why we fall for it, and how we can fight back.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;1-what-is-the-worse-than-average-effect&#34;&gt;&#xA;  1. What is the Worse-Than-Average Effect?&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#1-what-is-the-worse-than-average-effect&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Simply put, the &lt;strong&gt;Worse-Than-Average Effect&lt;/strong&gt; is the tendency to believe that we are below average at difficult tasks. While we generally overestimate our abilities on easy or familiar tasks (hello, illusory superiority!), when faced with challenges, a significant number of us assume we&amp;rsquo;re less skilled than our peers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
