<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Reasoning on Mind Traps: The Ultimate Guide to 150 Cognitive Biases</title>
    <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/tags/reasoning/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Reasoning on Mind Traps: The Ultimate Guide to 150 Cognitive Biases</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/tags/reasoning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Belief Bias</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/belief-bias/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/belief-bias/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Okay, here&amp;rsquo;s a blog post draft targeting the specified audience and structure, optimized for &amp;ldquo;Belief Bias&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:  Belief Bias: Why Your Brain Thinks What&amp;rsquo;s True Must Be Logical (Even When It Isn&amp;rsquo;t)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meta Description:&lt;/strong&gt; Belief Bias makes us accept flawed arguments simply because we agree with the conclusion. Learn how to recognize and overcome this cognitive trap to make better decisions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Body:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. What is Belief Bias?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Have you ever found yourself nodding along to an argument that felt…right, even if you couldn’t quite explain &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; it felt right? That might be the &lt;strong&gt;Belief Bias&lt;/strong&gt; at play. In its simplest form, Belief Bias is the tendency to evaluate the logical strength of an argument based on &lt;em&gt;whether you believe its conclusion is true.&lt;/em&gt; If the conclusion aligns with your existing beliefs, you&amp;rsquo;re more likely to see the argument as sound, even if it&amp;rsquo;s riddled with holes. Conversely, you&amp;rsquo;re more likely to dismiss a perfectly logical argument if the conclusion clashes with your worldview.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Grey Fallacy</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/grey-fallacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/grey-fallacy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Okay, here&amp;rsquo;s a blog post draft focusing on the Grey Fallacy, aiming to meet your specifications.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title: The Grey Fallacy: Why &amp;lsquo;Meeting in the Middle&amp;rsquo; Can Lead You Astray&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meta Description:&lt;/strong&gt; Are you falling victim to the Grey Fallacy? Learn how the belief that the truth lies between two extremes can distort your judgment and how to avoid it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. What is the Grey Fallacy?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Grey Fallacy, also known as the fallacy of the golden mean or the compromise fallacy, is the belief that the truth must lie somewhere in the middle between two opposing positions. It&amp;rsquo;s the assumption that a compromise or middle ground automatically represents the most accurate or reasonable stance. Think of it as automatically assuming that blending black and white &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; produces the &amp;ldquo;correct&amp;rdquo; shade of grey, regardless of the situation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Survivorship Bias</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/survivorship-bias/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/survivorship-bias/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Are you impressed by the dazzling success stories of entrepreneurs, athletes, or bestselling authors? Hold on a moment. Before you start rewriting your life plan, you need to understand &lt;strong&gt;Survivorship Bias&lt;/strong&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s a cognitive trap that can lead you to make seriously flawed decisions by focusing solely on the winners and overlooking the vast graveyard of those who didn&amp;rsquo;t make it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This post will dissect this powerful bias, exploring how it works, where it lurks, and how you can protect yourself from its insidious influence. Let&amp;rsquo;s dive in.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
