<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Coping on Mind Traps: The Ultimate Guide to 150 Cognitive Biases</title>
    <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/tags/coping/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Coping on Mind Traps: The Ultimate Guide to 150 Cognitive Biases</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/tags/coping/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Impact Bias</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/impact-bias/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/impact-bias/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve all been there: convinced that landing that dream job will be the pinnacle of happiness, or certain that failing an exam will ruin our lives forever. But more often than not, our feelings are more fleeting, and our resilience is stronger than we predict. This disconnect between our predictions and reality is due to something called &lt;strong&gt;Impact Bias&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. What is Impact Bias?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Simply put, &lt;strong&gt;Impact Bias&lt;/strong&gt; is the tendency to overestimate the length or the intensity of the impact of future feeling states. We tend to think both positive and negative events will have a much stronger and longer-lasting effect on our happiness (or unhappiness) than they actually do. So, that amazing promotion won&amp;rsquo;t guarantee lasting euphoria, and that disappointing rejection won&amp;rsquo;t result in perpetual misery.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ostrich Effect</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/ostrich-effect/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/ostrich-effect/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ever feel like you&amp;rsquo;d rather not check your bank balance after a spending spree? Or maybe you avoid reading articles about potential risks in your investment portfolio? You might be experiencing the &lt;strong&gt;Ostrich Effect&lt;/strong&gt;, a fascinating cognitive bias that can have surprisingly significant impacts on our lives. Let&amp;rsquo;s dig in and learn how to spot it and keep it from burying our heads in the sand.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;1-what-is-the-ostrich-effect&#34;&gt;&#xA;  1. What is the Ostrich Effect?&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#1-what-is-the-ostrich-effect&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Ostrich Effect&lt;/strong&gt; is the tendency to avoid negative information that might cause psychological discomfort. Just like the (incorrectly) perceived behavior of an ostrich burying its head in the sand to avoid danger, we sometimes choose to ignore bad news, hoping it will simply disappear.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
