<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sensory on Mind Traps: The Ultimate Guide to 150 Cognitive Biases</title>
    <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/tags/sensory/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Sensory on Mind Traps: The Ultimate Guide to 150 Cognitive Biases</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/tags/sensory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Modality Effect</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/modality-effect/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/modality-effect/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ever noticed how you seem to remember song lyrics far better than historical dates, even though you consciously studied the dates? Or how you grasp instructions better when someone &lt;em&gt;shows&lt;/em&gt; you rather than just &lt;em&gt;telling&lt;/em&gt; you? You might be experiencing the &lt;strong&gt;Modality Effect&lt;/strong&gt;, a fascinating cognitive bias that influences how we process and retain information based on the sensory channel through which it&amp;rsquo;s delivered.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;1-what-is-the-modality-effect&#34;&gt;&#xA;  1. What is the Modality Effect?&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#1-what-is-the-modality-effect&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Modality Effect&lt;/strong&gt; is the tendency to recall information more effectively when it&amp;rsquo;s presented through certain sensory modes (like auditory or visual) compared to others. Simply put, how information reaches your brain affects how well you remember it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weber–Fechner Law</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/weberfechner-law/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/weberfechner-law/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ever wondered why a $10 discount on a $100 item feels insignificant, but a $10 discount on a $20 item feels like a steal? You&amp;rsquo;re experiencing the &lt;strong&gt;Weber–Fechner Law&lt;/strong&gt; in action. This powerful cognitive bias shapes how we perceive change, impacting everything from our shopping habits to our strategic decisions. Understanding it can significantly improve your thinking and decision-making abilities. Let’s dive in.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;1-what-is-weberfechner-law&#34;&gt;&#xA;  1. What is Weber–Fechner Law?&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#1-what-is-weberfechner-law&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In its simplest form, the &lt;strong&gt;Weber–Fechner Law&lt;/strong&gt; states that &lt;em&gt;the perception of change in a stimulus is proportional to the magnitude of the initial stimulus.&lt;/em&gt; Think of it like this: the bigger something already is, the bigger the change needs to be for us to notice it meaningfully.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
