<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Economics on Mind Traps: The Ultimate Guide to 150 Cognitive Biases</title>
    <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/tags/economics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Economics on Mind Traps: The Ultimate Guide to 150 Cognitive Biases</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/tags/economics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Endowment Effect</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/endowment-effect/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/endowment-effect/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Okay, here&amp;rsquo;s a blog post draft targeting the specified audience and requirements.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title: Don&amp;rsquo;t Let Ownership Cloud Your Judgement: Understanding the Endowment Effect&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meta Description:&lt;/strong&gt; The Endowment Effect makes us overvalue what we own. Learn how this cognitive bias impacts decision-making in business, life, and learning, and discover strategies to overcome it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Ever tried selling something and felt like it was worth &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; more than anyone was willing to pay? Or clung to a stock long after the evidence suggested you should sell? You might be experiencing the &lt;strong&gt;Endowment Effect&lt;/strong&gt;, a cognitive bias that makes us irrationally attached to things simply because we own them. This isn&amp;rsquo;t just about sentimentality; it fundamentally alters how we assess value and can lead to poor decisions in all areas of life. Let&amp;rsquo;s unpack this powerful bias and learn how to keep it from clouding our judgment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Loss Aversion</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/loss-aversion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/loss-aversion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;stop-letting-loss-aversion-hijack-your-brain-how-to-make-smarter-decisions&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Stop Letting &amp;ldquo;Loss Aversion&amp;rdquo; Hijack Your Brain: How to Make Smarter Decisions&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#stop-letting-loss-aversion-hijack-your-brain-how-to-make-smarter-decisions&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Have you ever held onto a losing investment for &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; too long, or avoided a potentially beneficial change because you were afraid of the unknown? Chances are, you’ve been tripped up by &lt;strong&gt;Loss Aversion&lt;/strong&gt;, a powerful cognitive bias that shapes how we perceive and react to the world. Understanding this bias is crucial for better decision-making, whether you&amp;rsquo;re a student, a seasoned professional, or simply someone keen on improving their thinking.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Money Illusion</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/money-illusion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/money-illusion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;dont-be-fooled-understanding-the-money-illusion-and-how-to-beat-it&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Don&amp;rsquo;t Be Fooled: Understanding the Money Illusion and How to Beat It&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#dont-be-fooled-understanding-the-money-illusion-and-how-to-beat-it&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Ever felt richer after getting a raise, even though your cost of living also went up? You might be falling victim to the &lt;strong&gt;Money Illusion&lt;/strong&gt;, a sneaky cognitive bias that can cloud your judgment and lead to poor decisions. Let&amp;rsquo;s unpack this phenomenon and learn how to outsmart it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;1-what-is-money-illusion&#34;&gt;&#xA;  1. What is Money Illusion?&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#1-what-is-money-illusion&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Simply put, the &lt;strong&gt;Money Illusion&lt;/strong&gt; is the tendency to focus on the nominal value (face value) of money rather than its real value, which is its purchasing power. We often forget to account for inflation and how it erodes the actual amount of goods and services our money can buy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sunk Cost Fallacy</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/sunk-cost-fallacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/sunk-cost-fallacy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;stop-throwing-good-money-after-bad-understanding-the-sunk-cost-fallacy&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Stop Throwing Good Money After Bad: Understanding the Sunk Cost Fallacy&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#stop-throwing-good-money-after-bad-understanding-the-sunk-cost-fallacy&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Have you ever finished a terrible movie just because you’d already invested an hour into it? Or stayed in a dead-end job because you’d already put in five years? If so, you&amp;rsquo;ve experienced the &lt;strong&gt;Sunk Cost Fallacy&lt;/strong&gt;, a cognitive bias that trips up even the smartest among us. Understanding this bias can unlock better decision-making and help you avoid wasting valuable resources.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
