<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Comparison on Mind Traps: The Ultimate Guide to 150 Cognitive Biases</title>
    <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/tags/comparison/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Comparison on Mind Traps: The Ultimate Guide to 150 Cognitive Biases</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/tags/comparison/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Contrast Effect</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/contrast-effect/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/contrast-effect/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We make countless judgments every day. Is this job offer good? Is this news story accurate? Is this pain tolerable? What if I told you that your &lt;em&gt;perception&lt;/em&gt; of those things is heavily influenced by what you’ve just seen, heard, or experienced beforehand? Enter the &lt;strong&gt;Contrast Effect&lt;/strong&gt;, a cognitive bias that warps our judgment based on comparisons. Understanding it is crucial for making better decisions, both big and small.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;1-what-is-the-contrast-effect&#34;&gt;&#xA;  1. What is the Contrast Effect?&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#1-what-is-the-contrast-effect&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Simply put, the &lt;strong&gt;Contrast Effect&lt;/strong&gt; describes how our perception of something is influenced by a comparison with something else. It’s the enhancement or diminishing of a perception, cognition, or related performance that happens when we&amp;rsquo;re exposed to stimuli of different values along the same dimension. Think of it as your brain being a relative rather than an absolute measuring instrument.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distinction Bias</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/distinction-bias/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/distinction-bias/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We all want to make good decisions, whether it&amp;rsquo;s choosing the right job, investing wisely, or even just picking the best cereal at the grocery store. But our brains, brilliant as they are, sometimes play tricks on us. Today, we&amp;rsquo;re diving into a fascinating cognitive bias called &lt;strong&gt;Distinction Bias&lt;/strong&gt;, and how it can cloud your judgment.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;1-what-is-distinction-bias&#34;&gt;&#xA;  1. What is Distinction Bias?&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#1-what-is-distinction-bias&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distinction Bias&lt;/strong&gt; is the tendency to perceive two options as more different when evaluating them &lt;em&gt;simultaneously&lt;/em&gt; than when evaluating them &lt;em&gt;separately&lt;/em&gt;. Think of it like viewing the Grand Canyon and a local park together. The Grand Canyon will seem overwhelmingly majestic. But if you visited the local park on its own, you&amp;rsquo;d likely appreciate its beauty and tranquility much more.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Less-is-Better Effect</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/less-is-better-effect/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/less-is-better-effect/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever chosen the smaller gift basket over the larger one, even though the larger one clearly had more stuff? Or perhaps preferred the single, glowing review over a multitude of mixed ones? You might have been a victim of the &lt;strong&gt;Less-is-Better Effect&lt;/strong&gt;, a cognitive bias that trips us up more often than we realize.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this post, we&amp;rsquo;ll delve into this fascinating quirk of the mind, exploring why it happens, how it manifests in real life, and most importantly, how to protect ourselves from its sway. Get ready to rethink how you make decisions!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
