<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Creativity on Mind Traps: The Ultimate Guide to 150 Cognitive Biases</title>
    <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/tags/creativity/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Creativity on Mind Traps: The Ultimate Guide to 150 Cognitive Biases</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/tags/creativity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Cryptomnesia</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/cryptomnesia/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/cryptomnesia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Okay, here&amp;rsquo;s a blog post draft targeting your specified audience and structure, optimized for &amp;ldquo;Cryptomnesia&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Sneaky Thief of Originality: Understanding Cryptomnesia&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Ever had that &lt;em&gt;Eureka!&lt;/em&gt; moment where you felt like you’d stumbled upon the most ingenious idea imaginable? What if I told you that groundbreaking thought might not be so groundbreaking after all? Enter &lt;strong&gt;Cryptomnesia&lt;/strong&gt;, the subtle cognitive bias that can lead us to believe we’ve invented something completely original when, in fact, it&amp;rsquo;s a forgotten memory resurfacing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Functional Fixedness</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/functional-fixedness/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/functional-fixedness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve all been there: staring at a problem, convinced there&amp;rsquo;s no solution, when the answer is staring right at us… disguised as something else. This mental block is often caused by &lt;strong&gt;Functional Fixedness&lt;/strong&gt;, a cognitive bias that can stifle creativity, hinder problem-solving, and limit our understanding of the world. Let&amp;rsquo;s dive into what Functional Fixedness is, why it happens, and how to break free from its grip.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;1-what-is-functional-fixedness&#34;&gt;&#xA;  1. What is Functional Fixedness?&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#1-what-is-functional-fixedness&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Functional Fixedness&lt;/strong&gt; is the tendency to see an object only in the way it is traditionally used. It&amp;rsquo;s a mental constraint that prevents us from recognizing that an object designed for one purpose might also be useful for something completely different. Think of a hammer as &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; a tool for pounding nails, ignoring its potential as a paperweight, a doorstop, or even a makeshift weapon in a pinch (hopefully not!).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
