<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Marketing on Mind Traps: The Ultimate Guide to 150 Cognitive Biases</title>
    <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/tags/marketing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Marketing on Mind Traps: The Ultimate Guide to 150 Cognitive Biases</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/tags/marketing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Decoy Effect</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/decoy-effect/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/decoy-effect/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ever felt like you&amp;rsquo;re making a totally rational decision, only to realize later you were subtly nudged in a direction you hadn&amp;rsquo;t initially considered? Chances are, you&amp;rsquo;ve been a victim (or beneficiary!) of the &lt;strong&gt;Decoy Effect&lt;/strong&gt;. This cognitive bias plays a powerful role in our choices, influencing everything from what we eat to who we hire. Understanding it can help you become a more mindful and effective decision-maker.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;1-what-is-the-decoy-effect&#34;&gt;&#xA;  1. What is the Decoy Effect?&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#1-what-is-the-decoy-effect&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Simply put, the &lt;strong&gt;Decoy Effect&lt;/strong&gt; is the phenomenon where our preference between two options changes when we&amp;rsquo;re presented with a third, asymmetrically dominated option. This &amp;ldquo;decoy&amp;rdquo; is designed to make one of the original two choices look far more appealing, even if it&amp;rsquo;s not inherently better for us.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mere Exposure Effect</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/mere-exposure-effect/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/mere-exposure-effect/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever found yourself humming a song you initially disliked, or suddenly liking a brand you’ve seen advertised everywhere? Chances are, you’ve been influenced by the &lt;strong&gt;Mere Exposure Effect&lt;/strong&gt;, a cognitive bias that subtly shapes our preferences and decisions. Understanding this bias is crucial for anyone seeking clearer thinking, whether you’re a student, a professional, or simply a lifelong learner.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. What is Mere Exposure Effect?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Simply put, the &lt;strong&gt;Mere Exposure Effect&lt;/strong&gt; (also known as the familiarity principle) is the tendency to develop a preference for things merely because they are familiar. The more often we encounter something – a face, a song, a product, an idea – the more we tend to like it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
