<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Reward on Mind Traps: The Ultimate Guide to 150 Cognitive Biases</title>
    <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/tags/reward/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Reward on Mind Traps: The Ultimate Guide to 150 Cognitive Biases</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/tags/reward/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Hyperbolic Discounting</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/hyperbolic-discounting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/hyperbolic-discounting/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We all want the best for ourselves, right? We set goals, plan for the future, and envision the rewards that come with hard work. But how often do we find ourselves making decisions that seem to sabotage those very goals? The answer might lie in a sneaky cognitive bias called &lt;strong&gt;Hyperbolic Discounting&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. What is Hyperbolic Discounting?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Simply put, &lt;strong&gt;Hyperbolic Discounting&lt;/strong&gt; is the tendency to prefer a smaller reward now over a larger reward later, even if the larger reward is objectively better. And here’s the kicker: the closer the smaller reward is to the present, the stronger this preference becomes. Think of it as &amp;ldquo;instant gratification overdrive.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reward Devaluation Effect</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/reward-devaluation-effect/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/reward-devaluation-effect/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ever worked tirelessly towards a goal, only to feel a strange sense of… letdown once you’re close? That’s likely the &lt;strong&gt;Reward Devaluation Effect&lt;/strong&gt; kicking in. This cognitive bias, the tendency to devalue rewards one has already worked for but not yet received, can sabotage motivation and cloud our judgment. It’s time to understand how it works and how to combat it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. What is Reward Devaluation Effect?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Simply put, the &lt;strong&gt;Reward Devaluation Effect&lt;/strong&gt; is our tendency to see a reward as less appealing &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; we&amp;rsquo;ve put in significant effort to obtain it, but &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; we actually receive it. It&amp;rsquo;s like climbing a mountain, only to question its magnificence as you approach the summit.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
