<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Statistics on Mind Traps: The Ultimate Guide to 150 Cognitive Biases</title>
    <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/tags/statistics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Statistics on Mind Traps: The Ultimate Guide to 150 Cognitive Biases</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/tags/statistics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Illusory Correlation</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/illusory-correlation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/illusory-correlation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re all pattern-seeking creatures. Our brains are wired to find connections and make sense of the world around us. But sometimes, this inherent ability misfires, leading us to perceive relationships where none actually exist. This is the &lt;strong&gt;Illusory Correlation&lt;/strong&gt;, and understanding it is crucial for better thinking, decision-making, and navigating a world overflowing with information.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;1-what-is-illusory-correlation&#34;&gt;&#xA;  1. What is Illusory Correlation?&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#1-what-is-illusory-correlation&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Illusory Correlation&lt;/strong&gt; is the perception of a relationship between variables when no such relationship exists. In simpler terms, it’s seeing a connection where there isn’t one.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Look-Elsewhere Effect</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/look-elsewhere-effect/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/look-elsewhere-effect/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever felt a strong intuition about something, only to later realize you were cherry-picking information to fit your hunch? Or seen a conspiracy theory that seemed incredibly convincing&amp;hellip; until you realized it was based on selectively highlighting coincidences? You might have fallen victim to the &lt;strong&gt;Look-Elsewhere Effect&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This cognitive bias, simply put, is &lt;strong&gt;the tendency to see patterns in random data by disregarding the number of comparisons made.&lt;/strong&gt; It&amp;rsquo;s like searching a vast, random field for a specific wildflower. If you find &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; flower, you might feel like you&amp;rsquo;ve discovered something significant, conveniently forgetting the hours you spent sifting through countless weeds.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regression to the Mean</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/regression-to-the-mean/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/regression-to-the-mean/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever felt like your luck is changing after a particularly bad or good day? Maybe you celebrated a stellar sales month only to see things dip drastically next month. Or, perhaps you felt relieved after a disastrous exam result that was followed by a return to your usual performance. If so, you&amp;rsquo;ve encountered &lt;strong&gt;Regression to the Mean&lt;/strong&gt;, a sneaky cognitive bias that messes with our understanding of cause and effect.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Survivorship Bias</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/survivorship-bias/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/survivorship-bias/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Are you impressed by the dazzling success stories of entrepreneurs, athletes, or bestselling authors? Hold on a moment. Before you start rewriting your life plan, you need to understand &lt;strong&gt;Survivorship Bias&lt;/strong&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s a cognitive trap that can lead you to make seriously flawed decisions by focusing solely on the winners and overlooking the vast graveyard of those who didn&amp;rsquo;t make it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This post will dissect this powerful bias, exploring how it works, where it lurks, and how you can protect yourself from its insidious influence. Let&amp;rsquo;s dive in.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
