<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Value-Perception on Mind Traps: The Ultimate Guide to 150 Cognitive Biases</title>
    <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/tags/value-perception/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Value-Perception on Mind Traps: The Ultimate Guide to 150 Cognitive Biases</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/tags/value-perception/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Effort Justification</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/effort-justification/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/effort-justification/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;stop-wasting-your-effort-understanding-the-effort-justification-bias&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Stop Wasting Your Effort: Understanding the Effort Justification Bias&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#stop-wasting-your-effort-understanding-the-effort-justification-bias&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Ever spent hours assembling a piece of furniture only to convince yourself it&amp;rsquo;s the &lt;em&gt;best&lt;/em&gt; furniture you&amp;rsquo;ve ever owned, even though it wobbles precariously? You might be a victim of &lt;strong&gt;Effort Justification&lt;/strong&gt;, a cognitive bias that compels us to overvalue outcomes we&amp;rsquo;ve put significant effort into achieving. This seemingly harmless tendency can subtly warp our judgment and lead us down paths of inefficient or even harmful decisions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Endowment Effect</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/endowment-effect/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/endowment-effect/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Okay, here&amp;rsquo;s a blog post draft targeting the specified audience and requirements.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title: Don&amp;rsquo;t Let Ownership Cloud Your Judgement: Understanding the Endowment Effect&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meta Description:&lt;/strong&gt; The Endowment Effect makes us overvalue what we own. Learn how this cognitive bias impacts decision-making in business, life, and learning, and discover strategies to overcome it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Ever tried selling something and felt like it was worth &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; more than anyone was willing to pay? Or clung to a stock long after the evidence suggested you should sell? You might be experiencing the &lt;strong&gt;Endowment Effect&lt;/strong&gt;, a cognitive bias that makes us irrationally attached to things simply because we own them. This isn&amp;rsquo;t just about sentimentality; it fundamentally alters how we assess value and can lead to poor decisions in all areas of life. Let&amp;rsquo;s unpack this powerful bias and learn how to keep it from clouding our judgment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IKEA Effect</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/ikea-effect/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/ikea-effect/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;the-ikea-effect-why-you-overvalue-your-half-finished-projects&#34;&gt;&#xA;  The IKEA Effect: Why You Overvalue Your Half-Finished Projects&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#the-ikea-effect-why-you-overvalue-your-half-finished-projects&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Ever proudly display that wobbly bookshelf you painstakingly assembled from an IKEA flatpack, even though a professionally built one would be sturdier and look better? You might be experiencing the &lt;strong&gt;IKEA Effect&lt;/strong&gt;, a fascinating cognitive bias that skews our perception of value. This post will explore what the IKEA Effect is, why we fall for it, and how to avoid its pitfalls in our professional and personal lives.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Money Illusion</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/money-illusion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/money-illusion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;dont-be-fooled-understanding-the-money-illusion-and-how-to-beat-it&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Don&amp;rsquo;t Be Fooled: Understanding the Money Illusion and How to Beat It&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#dont-be-fooled-understanding-the-money-illusion-and-how-to-beat-it&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Ever felt richer after getting a raise, even though your cost of living also went up? You might be falling victim to the &lt;strong&gt;Money Illusion&lt;/strong&gt;, a sneaky cognitive bias that can cloud your judgment and lead to poor decisions. Let&amp;rsquo;s unpack this phenomenon and learn how to outsmart it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;1-what-is-money-illusion&#34;&gt;&#xA;  1. What is Money Illusion?&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#1-what-is-money-illusion&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Simply put, the &lt;strong&gt;Money Illusion&lt;/strong&gt; is the tendency to focus on the nominal value (face value) of money rather than its real value, which is its purchasing power. We often forget to account for inflation and how it erodes the actual amount of goods and services our money can buy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reward Devaluation Effect</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/reward-devaluation-effect/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/reward-devaluation-effect/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;the-reward-devaluation-effect-why-that-prize-doesnt-always-feel-so-prize-worthy&#34;&gt;&#xA;  The Reward Devaluation Effect: Why That Prize Doesn&amp;rsquo;t Always Feel So Prize-Worthy&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#the-reward-devaluation-effect-why-that-prize-doesnt-always-feel-so-prize-worthy&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Ever worked tirelessly towards a goal, only to feel a strange sense of… letdown once you’re close? That’s likely the &lt;strong&gt;Reward Devaluation Effect&lt;/strong&gt; kicking in. This cognitive bias, the tendency to devalue rewards one has already worked for but not yet received, can sabotage motivation and cloud our judgment. It’s time to understand how it works and how to combat it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
