<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Belief on Mind Traps: The Ultimate Guide to 150 Cognitive Biases</title>
    <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/tags/belief/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Belief on Mind Traps: The Ultimate Guide to 150 Cognitive Biases</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/tags/belief/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Confirmation Bias</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/confirmation-bias/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/confirmation-bias/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ever notice how easy it is to find &amp;ldquo;evidence&amp;rdquo; to support what you already believe? Whether it&amp;rsquo;s about politics, the best coffee shop, or the ideal investment strategy, we all tend to gravitate towards information that confirms our existing viewpoints. This is &lt;strong&gt;Confirmation Bias&lt;/strong&gt; at work, and understanding it is crucial for better thinking, smarter decisions, and more fruitful discussions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. What is Confirmation Bias?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Simply put, &lt;strong&gt;Confirmation Bias&lt;/strong&gt; is the tendency to search for, interpret, favor, and recall information in a way that validates our pre-existing beliefs or hypotheses. It&amp;rsquo;s like having a built-in echo chamber in your head, where opinions are constantly amplified and rarely challenged.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Subjective Validation</title>
      <link>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/subjective-validation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cognitive-biases.muthu.co/posts/subjective-validation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ever felt like a vague horoscope prediction eerily nailed your current situation? Or perhaps you clung to a conspiracy theory despite evidence against it? You might be experiencing &lt;strong&gt;Subjective Validation&lt;/strong&gt;, a cognitive bias that subtly shapes our beliefs and decisions. In this post, we&amp;rsquo;ll dissect this bias, explore its roots, uncover its consequences, and equip you with strategies to recognize and mitigate its influence on your thinking.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;1-what-is-subjective-validation&#34;&gt;&#xA;  1. What is Subjective Validation?&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#1-what-is-subjective-validation&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Simply put, &lt;strong&gt;Subjective Validation&lt;/strong&gt; is the tendency to perceive something as true if we &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; it to be true. It&amp;rsquo;s the phenomenon where our belief system actively seeks and interprets information in a way that confirms our pre-existing notions, regardless of the objective truth. Think of it as a mental echo chamber where our desires reverberate and amplify confirming evidence, while conveniently muffling dissenting voices.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
